<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Thibault Lestang - blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Code reviews in academia</title><link href="/blog/code-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Thibault Lestang</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-01-26:/blog/code-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Code reviewing is a standard practice among professional software
developers. In general terms, this means code is always subject to
human feedback, complementary to machine feedback such as output from
compilers, automatic linters and test runners. Indeed, code reviews
are most useful to look at aspects of software quality for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Code reviewing is a standard practice among professional software
developers. In general terms, this means code is always subject to
human feedback, complementary to machine feedback such as output from
compilers, automatic linters and test runners. Indeed, code reviews
are most useful to look at aspects of software quality for which
feedback cannot be automated, such as software design or code
readability.  In these cases, human feedback is crucial to ensure that
the code is written in a way that facilitates its study and reuse by
other developpers. In a commercial context, this could mean ensuring
that the software remains easy to debug, update and extend.  In other
words, code reviewing is about software sustainability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Code reviews also are a key component of open source software
developemnt.  Organised around platforms such as GitHub, GitLab or
SourceHut, contributors to open source software projects are able to
propose and discuss their contributions publicly. At the core of this
development model is the generally shared idea (across open source
developers) that contributed code isn't set in stone, and that several
rounds of feedback from other developers will be necessary for it the
be ready to be integrated into the larger project.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, in academia, research code is almost never reviewed.  Given
the tremendous importance of software in research, the previous
statement should come as a great surprise&amp;#x2026; but does it?  Within the
academic research process, software quality is a widely overlooked
topic, if not completely ignored.  This is because software rarely is
the end product, in contrast with the scientific results (&lt;i&gt;e.g&lt;/i&gt;
figures and tables) that it generates.  On top of that, the highly
competitive, publication rate-based funding system is not offering any
reward to to the researcher ready to dedicate time to writing good
software.  In fact, spending too much effort into software development
is often considered harmful for one's carreer, as it is detrimental to
the publication output.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 2021, it seems like the situation is slowly evolving, and has been
over the past ten years.  The "reproducibiliy crisis" opened many eyes
(and still does) to the fact many research works, in a wide range of
disciplines, cannot be reproduced by an independant team of
researchers.  A common cause of non-reproducibility stems from
software issues, &lt;i&gt;e.g&lt;/i&gt; the code being unavailable or left in an
unusable state after the main paper was published. Even though some
journals and funding bodies now require the code to be made available
at the time of publication, the large majority of research software is
still written by temporary staff (graduate students or post-doctoral
researchers), without formal training in software engineering, and
often operating under high pressure. As a result, an increasing number
of researchers experience the deep frustration of having to build upon
poorly written, undocumented, and untested software. This leads to an
increasing awareness that sacrificing software quality on the altar or
scientific productivity is very likely to backfire, actually &lt;i&gt;slowing
down&lt;/i&gt; research on the not-so-long run.  Consequently, many researchers
develop an interest and curiosity in programming and software
engineering, simply because "there must be a better way of doing
this".  In most cases, unfortunately, the knowledge gap is simply too
big to fill, especially for researcher-programmers in labs or research
groups that does not value software in the same way, and where
suitable mentors cannot be found.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Although most researchers are
aware of their relatively limited software engineering skillsgenerally
want to write better software
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
 In a academic
setting, this could mean ensuring that research code can be understood
by other researchers, as well as reused and built upon for further
researc prjects.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
 cannot be auto where machines cannot, for
instance software design an code readability
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
 beforecIt can take different forms in practice, but generally it means
feedback between developers working in a company or an open-source
project.  
&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>